MIKHAEL GASTER







Summary

Data scientist and researcher with experience in Python, NLP, quantitative social science research, software engineering, and technical consulting. Highlights of my background include collaborations with top academics, contributions to projects at a leading think tank, and high-stakes environmental consulting projects. Creative, enthusiastic, and responsible team player.

Technical Skill Highlights

- Python, Git, SQL, Excel, R, JS/TS/React
- Causal Inference, NLP, Experimental Design, Regression, Probability
- pandas, polars, bs4, HuggingFace, pytest, SQL, docker, Azure/cloud, networkx
- Plotly, Matplotlib, Excel/GSheets Charting

Experience

Data Science Research Fellow

2023 - Present

The Jain Family Institute / Center for Active Stewardship

Full stack lead/solo developer for our flagship database, which replaces a \$100k/year commercial product. Duties included parsing, normalizing, and correcting data from public financial filings; creating and deploying our database via a public API; creating an interactive front-end display of the database. Also performed various published analyses of the parsed data. Utilized a wide range of tools ranging from pure Python to SQL, LLMs, text embedding, clustering, FastAPI, docker, and graph algorithms.

Natural Language Processing Research Assistant

2023 - 2024

Oxford University / The Industrial Policy Group

Spearheaded the development and improvement of text classification workflows underpinning landmark research papers. ¹² Improved model accuracy from 87% to 94%. Collaborated with leading professors and guided junior colleagues. Transitioned workflow to GPU cloud computing. Derived feature importance from fine-tuned LLMs. Used LLMs to extract and normalize entity names, descriptions, and abbreviations from text. Implemented professional best practices, including version control and testing protocols.

Associate (Data Science and Analytics Consultant)

2021 - 2022

Deetken Insight Consulting

Developed a comparable static CGE model to estimate the economic impacts of BC's climate policies on sectors, households, demographic groups, commodities, and more. My proposal won the \$150k bid.

Other projects included a forensic audit of a major utility's environmental/financial modelling, and a project described as "hands down one of, if not the, best consulting engagements we have commissioned."

Education

M.A. in Economics

2020-2021

The University of British Columbia 4.3 / 4.33

B.A. in Economics & Mathematics

2020-2021

The University of British Columbia

4.0 / 4.33

Interests

- Data science for good (pro-bono, etc.)
- Chess: 2100+ rating (lichess)

■ Prediction markets: 300%+ ROI

■ Cooking, reading, soccer, meditation